<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>startups on Sunil Rao</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/tags/startups/</link>
    <description>Recent content in startups on Sunil Rao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/tags/startups/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Make it a cog in YOUR machine</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/your-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/your-machine/</guid>
      <description>In your work, you must either be a visionary, mercenary, apprentice, craftsman, explorer. You can’t be more than one of these at any given time - at least within one context. And you must know which one you are in each context. If you’re not the one you thought you’d be in a particular context, you’ll find yourself frustrated or stuck.
Visionary: You’re working towards an end of your own design and selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why are you joining a startup?</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/dont-join-startup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/dont-join-startup/</guid>
      <description>Don&amp;rsquo;t join a startup just for it’s mission. Of course you shouldn’t join a company selling opioids or sugary drinks, that would certainly be a Bad Thing. But do not expect it to affect or shape your experience much at all. The reality of working in even the most compassionate startup is that:
The mission becomes an abstraction that you work towards, using general purpose tools and structures (e.g. a marketplace is a marketplace and cares about things like GMV and liquidity, regardless of whether you’re facilitating home rentals or dog walks).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
