<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>work on Sunil Rao</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/tags/work/</link>
    <description>Recent content in work on Sunil Rao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/tags/work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Make it a cog in YOUR machine</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/your-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/your-machine/</guid>
      <description>In your work, you must either be a visionary, mercenary, apprentice, craftsman, explorer. You can’t be more than one of these at any given time - at least within one context. And you must know which one you are in each context. If you’re not the one you thought you’d be in a particular context, you’ll find yourself frustrated or stuck.
Visionary: You’re working towards an end of your own design and selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some scattered observations: You probably shouldn’t join a startup</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/dont-join-startup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/dont-join-startup/</guid>
      <description>Don&amp;rsquo;t join a startup just for it’s mission. Of course you shouldn’t join a company selling opioids or sugary drinks, that would certainly be a Bad Thing. But do not expect it to affect or shape your experience much at all. The reality of working in even the most compassionate startup is that:
The mission becomes an abstraction that you work towards, using general purpose tools and structures (e.g. a marketplace is a marketplace and cares about things like GMV and liquidity, regardless of whether you’re facilitating home rentals or dog walks).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On infinite games, meaning at work &amp; noblesse oblige</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/infinite-games-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/infinite-games-work/</guid>
      <description>I loved the way Max Nussbaum called attention to the dysfunction of how we often seek to find meaning at work. It prompted a lengthier reflection than anticipated, and thought it was worth reproducing here.
—
I think a function of paying lots of attention to the superstars of the tech world and aching after our next big success is that we almost become disdainful of the everyday opportunities to make meaning you mention - to be kind, share a moment, act honorably, and laugh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“How to Do What You Love” needs a prequel</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/how-to-do-what-you-love-needs-a-prequel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 01:29:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/how-to-do-what-you-love-needs-a-prequel/</guid>
      <description>“To do something well you have to like it,” Paul Graham famously wrote. This advice can come like a friendly slap in the face. Of course! Striving to excel in a domain that does not interest us is obviously silly. But are we capable of liking something long enough - and without grasping at it and suffocating it - to do it well?
Some thoughts from others:
Andrew Yang: “They need status and reassurance…They think in two years, not 20.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
