<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Sunil Rao</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Sunil Rao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>&#43;560k housing units for NYC by 2030</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/nyc-housing230-tracker/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/nyc-housing230-tracker/</guid>
      <description>A recent study suggests that NYC needs to build 560k additional units overall by 2030.
Since the NYC&amp;rsquo;s government publicly tracks only the number of affordable housing units getting built, I&amp;rsquo;ve started a tracker that compiles all active and potential legislative initiatives that could yield more housing in order to establish a concrete sense of our current trajectory, and make clear if and how that is insufficient.
Note that the 560 units target should probably be considered a bare minimum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Economic policy, growth, and human flourishing</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/growth-policy-flourishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/growth-policy-flourishing/</guid>
      <description>What do scientific innovation, economic policy, GDP, employment, and entrepreneurship have to do with increasing flourishing at scale?
I’ve put a pin in this project for now, and I&amp;rsquo;m parking my observations, questions for further research and brief summaries of some key readings here.
Observations I noticed two schools of thought emerge from my research.
The first, Camp Progress, is intensely considered with raising living standards, and supporting a talented elite driving this forward for all of society.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Listening to music in the 21st century</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/music_appreciation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/music_appreciation/</guid>
      <description>How might I stop and appreciate music more?
My musical life has been a bit stuck. I find myself not getting too excited about music these days. Maybe this is not really a problem. Or, perhaps this is just a result of my taking myself and my existential crises too seriously.
Probably a bit of both. But I think there is another factor.
I wonder if the emerging structure of music - e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practicing active recall</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/a-simple-redo-log-for-the-gmat-copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 03:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/a-simple-redo-log-for-the-gmat-copy/</guid>
      <description>One of my teachers during freshman year of high school encouraged us to write down at the end of each day what we&amp;rsquo;d learned that day, as a way to internalize new concepts.
It was a nice idea. Wish I could say I followed through!
Fast forward twelve (!!) years later, and my GMAT instructor emphasizes that keeping an error log and redoing problems is the #1 way to raise your GMAT Score.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building win-win commercial gyms</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/building-win-win-commercial-gyms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 20:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/building-win-win-commercial-gyms/</guid>
      <description>The premise: Commercial gyms generally want you to buy a subscription and never use it. More than 70 million Americans had a gym membership last year, but only 18% went consistently. All 70 million paid an average of $58 per month for their membership. And if you do go - especially at a reasonable hour - the equipment you need could be occupied. We’re seriously still doing this?
For many, home/outdoor fitness does the job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduce spaced repetition for more learning on Brilliant</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 18:04:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been using Brilliant for a few weeks now. In the last few years, reading the works of Nassim Taleb on probability, randomness and complex systems rekindled my desire to learn probability and statistics. Instead of brushing off some rather dreary-looking textbooks in order to refresh my foundations, I decided to turn to Brilliant instead after stumbling upon its wonderful culture page.
The emphasis on learning by doing has been refreshing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
