<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Sunil Rao</title>
    <link>https://relaxed-wilson-de5218.netlify.app/projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Sunil Rao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 03:30:33 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://relaxed-wilson-de5218.netlify.app/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A simple redo log for the GMAT</title>
      <link>https://relaxed-wilson-de5218.netlify.app/projects/a-simple-redo-log-for-the-gmat-copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 03:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaxed-wilson-de5218.netlify.app/projects/a-simple-redo-log-for-the-gmat-copy/</guid>
      <description>One of my teachers during freshman year of high school encouraged us to write down at the end of each day what we&amp;rsquo;d learned that day, as a way to internalize new concepts.
It was a nice idea. Wish I could say I followed through!
Fast forward twelve (!!) years later, and my GMAT instructor emphasizes that keeping an error log and redoing problems is the #1 way to raise your GMAT Score.
This time around, I listened up. In hindsight, I probably could have done an even better job committing to my redo&amp;rsquo;s.
Problems would pile up on the error log.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building win-win commercial gyms</title>
      <link>https://relaxed-wilson-de5218.netlify.app/projects/building-win-win-commercial-gyms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 20:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaxed-wilson-de5218.netlify.app/projects/building-win-win-commercial-gyms/</guid>
      <description>The premise: Commercial gyms generally want you to buy a subscription and never use it. More than 70 million Americans had a gym membership last year, but only 18% went consistently. All 70 million paid an average of $58 per month for their membership. And if you do go - especially at a reasonable hour - the equipment you need could be occupied. We’re seriously still doing this?
For many, home/outdoor fitness does the job. Many of us are familiar with P90X or, more recently, things like Mirror, that require minimal equipment. And perhaps the pandemic will accelerate the trend towards non-gym fitness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduce spaced repetition for more learning on Brilliant</title>
      <link>https://relaxed-wilson-de5218.netlify.app/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 18:04:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaxed-wilson-de5218.netlify.app/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been using Brilliant for a few weeks now. In the last few years, reading the works of Nassim Taleb on probability, randomness and complex systems rekindled my desire to learn probability and statistics. Instead of brushing off some rather dreary-looking textbooks in order to refresh my foundations, I decided to turn to Brilliant instead after stumbling upon its wonderful culture page.
The emphasis on learning by doing has been refreshing. I appreciate that Brilliant provides instruction along the way instead of dumping it upfront. And I never fail to appreciate the reminders after I get a problem wrong…that without getting stumped, there is no learning!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
