<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Sunil Rao</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Sunil Rao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>No-code 101</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/no-code101/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/no-code101/</guid>
      <description>I think there are a four sub-areas under the umbrella of no-code:
1. App-builders for wantrapreneurs. While there are some questions around how scalable these platforms are, for founders trying to find PMF, no-code is right now a much more resourceful/efficient approach than teaching yourself to code or hiring a developer. Even coders will use these as a faster way to test an idea.
A couple of fast-growing startups here are Bubble (a full-stack no-code dev platform that I used for my EdTech app) and Webflow (loved by designers).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting the most out of ODNC</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/odnc-reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/odnc-reflection/</guid>
      <description>If you are a new no-code maker - which was me at the start of ODNC1 - this is for you! As Anthony Constantino reminded me, it can be very helpful to learn from those who are just a step or two ahead of you in the process, moreso than more than advanced practitioners. So hopefully my reflections will be useful to you.
On the creative process There’s a lot of great guidance and playbooks on creating software products out there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On infinite games, meaning at work &amp; noblesse oblige</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/infinite-games-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/infinite-games-work/</guid>
      <description>I loved the way Max Nussbaum called attention to the dysfunction of how we often seek to find meaning at work. It prompted a lengthier reflection than anticipated, and thought it was worth reproducing here.
—
I think a function of paying lots of attention to the superstars of the tech world and aching after our next big success is that we almost become disdainful of the everyday opportunities to make meaning you mention - to be kind, share a moment, act honorably, and laugh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning and not flailing</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/flail-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/flail-learn/</guid>
      <description>As a freshman in high school, one of my teachers encouraged us to write down what we’d learned at school at the end of everyday. A simple way to practice active recall. Number of times I did this? Zero.
I did pretty well in high school. I was happy to burn the midnight oil and delay gratification. I got into Stanford and a bunch of other top schools. It worked.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On learning from mistakes</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/learning_from_mistakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/learning_from_mistakes/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s good to learn from your mistakes. It&amp;rsquo;s better to learn from other people&amp;rsquo;s mistakes.&amp;quot;
 -Warren Buffett
This one’s always been a bee in my bonnet. It inspired a rather neurotic energy and sense of behind-ness. So many biographies to read, so many interviews to listen to. But having given myself chances to make my own mistakes in recent years, I’ve come to the conclusion: you can’t learn from others mistakes until you’ve first begun to learn from your own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Craft Sports</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/craft-sports/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/craft-sports/</guid>
      <description>As an avid sports fan/weekend warrior, I hate to see sports readily dismissed in Serious Talk about what can make for meaning, stronger communities and a stronger country.
One reason, as Helen Toner mentions, is that Serious Intellectuals don’t take sports seriously.
I think another reason sports don’t figure prominently into 21st century meaning-making is that major sports are very “top-down.” They’re not very friendly to individual meaning-making or even local community identity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WIP study guide #3: The Kegan Model</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/wip-study-guide-3-the-kegan-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 04:04:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/wip-study-guide-3-the-kegan-model/</guid>
      <description>Several friends and mentors of mine have suffered the misfortune of lending me their ears during my Kegan phase. For the uninitiated, Robert Kegan has proposed a fascinating and encouraging model of psychological development that continues well into adulthood - which, one learns, was not previously generally accepted. This is sort of a cheat-post - I repurpose what I wrote from an email exchange my attempt (only what I wrote) to put Kegan’s work in my words and reflect on it’s applicability, lightly edited for clarity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Highlights that don&#39;t make the reel</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/highlights-that-dont-make-the-reel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 01:56:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/highlights-that-dont-make-the-reel/</guid>
      <description>The headlines after the 0-0 draw at Old Trafford were sadly predictable. “Man United, Chelsea show why Premier League title challenge is beyond them.”
My favorite shot from that game (though let’s be honest it didn’t have much competition…tehe) was of Thiago Silva and Edinson Cavani connecting after the final whistle. Silva puts his hand on his former teammate’s shoulder…you can imagine these guys have so much to talk about. The warmth is obvious.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“How to Do What You Love” needs a prequel</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/how-to-do-what-you-love-needs-a-prequel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 01:29:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/how-to-do-what-you-love-needs-a-prequel/</guid>
      <description>“To do something well you have to like it,” Paul Graham famously wrote. This advice can come like a friendly slap in the face. Of course! Striving to excel in a domain that does not interest us is obviously silly. But are we capable of liking something long enough - and without grasping at it and suffocating it - to do it well?
Some thoughts from others:
Andrew Yang: “They need status and reassurance…They think in two years, not 20.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WIP study guide #2: Classical Antiquity...</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/wip-study-guide-1-classical-antiquity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 22:00:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/wip-study-guide-1-classical-antiquity/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;the Greco-Roman world, centered on the Mediterranean, of the 8th century BC and the 6th century AD. Why is the classical antiquity period significant?
Western civilization - modernity - was born of a mix of the classical and the Christian. And the recent history of the world - for the last several hundred years, until recently - has been the history of westernization or modernization of the whole world: scientific ideas/methods, new ways of thinking, military technology, and public administration fueling greater power and wealth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WIP study guide #1: takeaways from “Political Economy 101”</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/takeaways-from-political-economy-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 14:43:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/takeaways-from-political-economy-101/</guid>
      <description>A few months ago, I set out to give myself an introduction to “something like” political economy. It was a conveniently vague way to assemble a reading plan around some things I’d been wanting to read for a while at the intersection of philosophy, economics, history and technology.
Though a bit scattered, doing this surfaced a few distinct topics and questions for me to pursue in future:
1. Epistemology, or the “theory of knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It’s Time to Play</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/its-time-to-play/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 02:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/its-time-to-play/</guid>
      <description>If today’s toys are tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s tech, then we must also start to play. Building on Marc Andreesen’s landmark essay, Tanner Greer identifies the source of our inability to build in recent cultural and social changes. A culture that seeks to solve problems by persuading and deferring to authorities, as we seem to do now - rather than through individual or collective self-reliance, as we used to in this country - will not build.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trade globally, love locally.</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/trade-globally-love-locally/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 22:28:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/trade-globally-love-locally/</guid>
      <description>A short summary of Russ Roberts&#39; How Adam Smith Can Change Your Life Self-interest and incentives are how we take care of people we don’t know and organize large-scale systems. This is the subject matter of the Wealth of Nations. But we must also practice virtue, conscience, warmth, dignity, nobility amongst our inner circles in order to live a good life. This is the subject of the Theory of Moral Sentiments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The link between antitrust and inequality</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/the-link-between-antitrust-and-inequality-jonathan-teppers-the-myth-of-capitalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 16:11:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/the-link-between-antitrust-and-inequality-jonathan-teppers-the-myth-of-capitalism/</guid>
      <description>The Myth of Capitalism, by Jonathan Tepper In summary: Current, unacceptable levels of inequality stem from the deterioration of antitrust enforcement and the subsequent “toll road-ization” of the American economy. Mergers permitted without scrutiny, oligopoly proliferates; workers, customers, suppliers get squeezed. This deterioration was driven by revolving doors, cronyism, and Chicago economic philosophy. This is all exacerbated by concentrated ownership of these toll roads by the wealthy.
Questions &amp;amp; Review Tepper&amp;rsquo;s story is enticingly simple.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools for thought = mental bureaucracy?</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/tools-for-thought-mental-bureaucracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 17:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/tools-for-thought-mental-bureaucracy/</guid>
      <description>*This is a hot take, quite happy to be disagreed with and told why I&amp;rsquo;m wrong*
I think focusing on using tools for thought can easily turn into the construction of a suffocating educational bureaucracy. It’s utopian high-modernism applied to independent learning.
What if it’s better to just learn things that really makes us burn with curiosity and desire, that make us want to keep building on that foundation and go deeper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build Local Soccer</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/build-local-soccer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 20:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/build-local-soccer/</guid>
      <description>We don’t just tune into the Premier League for the highest-quality soccer. Or for the fantastic coverage team at NBC. Or even for Kyle Martino’s earring.
We also tune in so that we can take part in European soccer culture. It’s the pageantry, the songs, the chants, the pasty-faced British guys who just got out of the same pre-match pub their grandfathers went to. All these mark a sense of tradition, loyalty between club and community, and community ownership of the the club - if not in financial or legal terms, than at least in spirit - that predate big-time commercialization of the sport.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yes-and political economy: notes on Breaking Smart, Season 1.</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/yes-and-political-economy-notes-on-breaking-smart-season-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 19:18:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/yes-and-political-economy-notes-on-breaking-smart-season-1/</guid>
      <description>Ride the software wave or cling to a sinking ship
Software is a rare general-purpose soft technology (writing, money) that is transforming, upending the industrial social order, creating dramatic win-lose situations based on who appreciates and gets on the right side of its impact.
We’re just at the beginning - infra has only just gotten in place for deployment, it operates under other labels (e.g. genomics innovation driven by software), and has been driven by politically non-confrontational youth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A very (very very) short introduction to socialism</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/a-very-very-very-short-introduction-to-socialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 19:05:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/a-very-very-very-short-introduction-to-socialism/</guid>
      <description>My notes on the first section of OUP&amp;rsquo;s Socialism: A Very Short Introduction, which covers socialism&amp;rsquo;s various theories and traditions The general idea  Commitment to the creation of an egalitarian society (equality of resources, rights, opportunities). That inheritance of capital/wealth provides a few with immense privilege; meanwhile, a cycle of deprivation limits opportunities and influence for the rest. Ergo, private property prevents any hope of equality. Optimistic view of human beings’ willingness to cooperate with one other on large scale.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Under the yoke of growth: Timothy Shenk&#39;s essay, &#34;Apostles of Growth&#34;</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/under-the-yoke-of-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 21:44:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/under-the-yoke-of-growth/</guid>
      <description>Summary and takeaways from the Timothy Shenk essay in The Nation. Historians of capitalism describe the discovery of deliberate economic growth its consequences. They chronicle the operations of the “relentless logic of capitalism,” and how growth has became (and remains) our master at the expense of a commitment to justice.
The point that growth has become our master seems true to me. At company-level and federal level, we seem to contort ourselves and our environments to show growth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is political freedom limited by economic freedom? Notes on Hayek&#39;s &#34;The Road to Serfdom.&#34;</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/is-political-freedom-limited-by-economic-freedom-notes-on-hayeks-the-road-to-serfdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 18:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/is-political-freedom-limited-by-economic-freedom-notes-on-hayeks-the-road-to-serfdom/</guid>
      <description>2-sentence summary: Socialism is incompatible with freedom. It leads to fascism and dictatorship.
Observations and avenues for further investigation  I wonder if Hayek mischaracterizes the socialist/egalitarian view on economic freedom and its relation to political freedom…If he underestimates the importance of / extent to which society must go to support every individual’s economic freedom in order to assure political freedom. Socialism seems &amp;ldquo;nice.&amp;quot; We get to bathe in our good intentions, celebrate our niceness and shared values.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toni Morrison’s &#34;Sula&#34; &amp; playing with meaning</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/toni-morrisons-sula-playing-with-meaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 17:43:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/toni-morrisons-sula-playing-with-meaning/</guid>
      <description>This was my first Toni Morrison book, and it was magnificent. It is clear as you read it that a master is at work. You feel you are in the palm of her hand, and you like it that way.
Horrifying and painful yet life-affirming all at once. Dramatic but in a playful, deft way. Compassionate but not pitying. Pensive but not preachy or judgmental. Especially on this last note - this novel brought back to mind David Chapman’s schematic of predominant stances toward meaning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CBT for economic history: Albert Hirschman on &#34;Political Economics and Possibilism&#34;</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/cbt-for-economic-history-albert-hirschman-on-political-economics-and-possibilism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 21:32:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/cbt-for-economic-history-albert-hirschman-on-political-economics-and-possibilism/</guid>
      <description>Summary  We tend to be short-sighted, impractical and overly pessimistic interpreters and agents of change. The search for (and the assumption that there exist) general laws whose continuous unfolding explains change over time can backfire. By passing history through his “possibilist” filters, Hirschman “[defends] the right to a nonprojected future as one of the truly inalienable rights of every person and nation.”  How this squares with other perspectives:  This squares nicely with Taleb’s view that “we are better at doing than explaining” and his low opinion of the “Soviet-Harvard complex,” as well as with Hayek’s talk of “man’s fatal striving to control society.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summarizing Russ Roberts&#39; &#34;Gambling with Other People&#39;s Money&#34;</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/summarizing-russ-roberts-gambling-with-other-peoples-money/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 14:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/summarizing-russ-roberts-gambling-with-other-peoples-money/</guid>
      <description>Summary The government bailed out debt-holders in a series of bank failures in the 70&amp;rsquo;s through the 90&amp;rsquo;s, signaling an implicit guarantee of creditors. This implicit guarantee combined with a politician-driven effort starting in the 90’s to orchestrate an increase in homeownership led to excessive use of leverage by Wall Street and aspiring homeowners to finance increasingly risky investments in housing in the 00&amp;rsquo;s. This in turn allowed Wall Street and politicians to privatize gains ($$, votes) and socialize eventual losses to taxpayers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Hayek&#39;s &#34;The Pretense of Knowledge&#34; (1974)</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/notes-on-hayeks-the-pretense-of-knowledge-1974/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 19:02:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/notes-on-hayeks-the-pretense-of-knowledge-1974/</guid>
      <description>Key Takeaways:
 “men’s fatal striving to control society—a striving which makes him not only a tyrant over his fellows, but which may well make him the destroyer of a civilization which no brain has designed but which has grown from the free efforts of millions of individuals.” No knowledge &amp;gt; some “knowledge” if it forces you to act with some humility and avoid decisions with big, unintended, difficult-to-reverse, negative consequences Gardener &amp;gt; Craftsman, when it comes to social order.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reaction to Emily Wilson’s The Odyssey, Wonder and Education</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/reaction-to-emily-wilsons-the-odyssey-wonder-and-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 21:38:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/reaction-to-emily-wilsons-the-odyssey-wonder-and-education/</guid>
      <description>How I picked it up: Tyler Cowen named it his best book of 2018. Tyler called this a “joy to read” and praised Wilson’s introductory essay. I agree with this assessment, and I’ll add to this by singling out Wilson’ Translator’s Note, which I think is the book’s hidden gem:
“When I was eight years old, my primary school put on a production of a (much-shortened) Odyssey, complete with costumes, song, and dance…It was a turning point in my life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something like political economy</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/intro_political_economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/intro_political_economy/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been an avid reader/listener of Marginal Revolution, EconTalk, Conversations with Tyler, and Nassim Nicholas Taleb&amp;rsquo;s works for a few years now.
I took a handful of great classes at Stanford covering related subjects: &amp;ldquo;History of Capitalism&amp;rdquo; with Jennifer Burns, &amp;ldquo;American Economic History&amp;rdquo; with Gavin Wright, &amp;ldquo;The Relations Between Philosophical Enquiry and Historical Enquiry&amp;rdquo; with Rahul Chaudhri, and &amp;ldquo;Capitalism and its Discontents&amp;rdquo; with Sean Hanretta and J.P. Daughton.
I read Niall Ferguson, Jonathan Levy, Albert Hirschman and Emma Rothschild books in my free time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing guidance</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/writing_guidance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/writing_guidance/</guid>
      <description>Gleb Posobin &amp;ldquo;Your own ideas mostly seem trivial to you because you have the right concept structures in place to support them. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t come up with these ideas otherwise. So it&amp;rsquo;s easier to notice your own ideas in a dialogue: your friend has different concept structures and notices them.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Corollary: don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to say obvious things.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Corollary 2: it is ok if it seems to you that you do not have nontrivial ideas of your own.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
