<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Hugo Site</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on A Hugo Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This is a customized copyright.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 04:04:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Summarizing Russ Roberts&#39; &#34;Gambling with Other People&#39;s Money&#34;</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/summarizing-russ-roberts-gambling-with-other-peoples-money/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 14:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/summarizing-russ-roberts-gambling-with-other-peoples-money/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/summarizing-russ-roberts-gambling-with-other-peoples-money/ -&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government bailed out debt-holders in a series of bank failures in the 70&amp;rsquo;s through the 90&amp;rsquo;s, signaling an implicit guarantee of creditors. This implicit guarantee combined with a politician-driven effort starting in the 90’s to orchestrate an increase in homeownership led to excessive use of leverage by Wall Street and aspiring homeowners to finance increasingly risky investments in housing in the 00&amp;rsquo;s. This in turn allowed Wall Street and politicians to privatize gains ($$, votes) and socialize eventual losses to taxpayers. The use of excessive leverage turns a failure into a meltdown. Rescues distort the natural feedback loop of capitalism. We are less capitalist than we would like to admit. We don’t need to more precisely engineer our financial system; we need to reintroduce “skin in the game.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;qa-style-notes&#34;&gt;Q&amp;amp;A-style notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What role did housing policy and politicians play?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Originally a tool to correct market failure, GSE’s became a tool for politicians to get wins by increasing home ownership…playing with other people’s money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because of the government guarantee, [banks] could borrow money cheaply. They could then earn money by buying mortgages that paid a higher rate of interest than the rate Fannie and Freddie had to pay to their lenders. It was a money machine that was incredibly profitable. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fannie and Freddie increased liquidity to the mortgage market by buying loans from mortgage originators. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pressure from politicians makes Fannie/Freddie a tool to increase home ownership, leading to many riskier loans being made with implicit guarantee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;between 1998 and 2003, Fannie and Freddie played an important role in pushing up the demand for housing at the low end of the mar- ket. That in turn made subprime loans increasingly attractive to other financial institutions as the prices of houses rose steadily. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since they were supporting riskier loans, they played an important role in growth of subprime MBS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What role did commercial and investment banks play?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explanation #1: hubris, greed, and myopia— irrational exuberance run wild. That they believed housing prices and MBS prices would continue to climb, so they were happy to keep selling and buying MBS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Problems with explanation #1:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least some practitioners (and probably fewer than we know about) did see it coming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it wasn’t really the same asset appreciating year after year…The proportion of the mortgage market that was subprime was increasing. The investors were lending money to finance increasingly risky loans. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the banks invested in the safest mortgage-backed products…if they really were so exuberant, why not get even riskier?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explanation #2: Rather than make super-risky bets, banks could make bets w/ smaller upside and higher chance of success, and gain bigger returns through the use of leverage. So they didn’t need to be shooting for inside straights. Executives could make tons of money for themselves by just “picking up nickels in front of a steamroller.” They knew that by the time the music stopped, they’d have nothing to lose and they’d already have made so much money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Wall Street] lobbied for policy decisions that created the mess [which ones? The change in capital requirements? Implicit creditor guarantee?]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But even if debt-holders expected to get bailed out, there are still equity-holders. Why didn’t they restrain the riskiness of the major players?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because they’d been making money as stock prices (and revenue) rose in response to these risky bets, and they didn’t have all their eggs in one basket. Content to let things ride.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But executives of these lenders were also big equity holders, and their personal wealth was surely more concentrated in their companies? Why didn’t they constrain risk-taking?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The downside risk is cushioned by his ability to accumulate [big] salary and bonuses [via leverage] in advance of failure. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;expected returns to bank executives from bad investments can be quite large even when the effects on the firm are quite harmful. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They didn’t intend to have their banks collapse, their cards just didn’t come true this time. Which is okay, because they already made tons of money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You’ve borrow money to make other loans. So when those loans default, you don’t have much to lose. And you were making money up until that point, so you had upside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financing their salaries by “leveraging” implicit government backing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The standard explanations for the meltdown on Wall Street are that executives were overconfident. Or they believed their models that assumed Gaussian distributions of risk when the distributions actu- ally had fat tails. Or they believed the ratings agencies. Or they believed that housing prices couldn’t fall. Or they believed some permutation of these many explanations. 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These have some truth, but the larger issue is that they bank decision-makers had very little to lose from their banks failing, and had already made out like bandits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why did mortgage lenders get comfortable lending to people putting no money down?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(First potential reason is you believe housing prices are just going to go up, so you just don’t think it’s that risky to do so.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second reason is that you will be very comfortable lending the money if you know you can sell the loan to someone else.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;most frequent buyers of loans were the GSEs Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fannie and Freddie bought those loans with borrowed money. Fannie and Freddie were able to borrow the money because lenders were confident that Uncle Sam stood behind Fannie and Freddie. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What role did new financial regulation play?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actually, not huge…the biggest issue remains implicit guarantee to creditors…rational exuberance, that was made rational because you were gambling with other people’s money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Looser capital requirements did create an incentive to hide risky investments under the AAA label, allowing banks to use more leverage
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tranching system of CDOs was a way to create AAA-rated investments out of loans that were highly risky. This financial alchemy was particularly attractive because of the regulatory change.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How did this work?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But aren’t taxpayers also homeowners? If so, what exactly is the problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The set of taxpayers is not the same set of people that became homeowners. So most people got nothing out of this except a tax bill. And for those that did get homes, good money was used to fund something that soon became worth much less. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other factors?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Though other factors—the repeal of the Glass-Steagall Act, predatory lending, fraud, changes in capital requirements, and so on—made things worse, I focus on creditor rescue, housing policy, tax policy, and monetary policy because without these policies and their interaction, the crisis would not have occurred at all. And among causes, I focus on creditor rescue and housing policy because they are the most misunderstood. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shocking numbers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By 2005, 43 percent of first-time buyers were putting no money down, and 68 percent were putting down less than 10 percent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Market for subprime MBS] “grew steadily from $100 billion in 2000 to over $600 billion in 2006.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fannie and Freddie bought 25.2% of the record $272.81 billion in subprime MBS sold in the first half of 2006&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Tangent: What is a CDS? **&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;W/r to a particular asset, I (seller of CDS) will pay you (buyer of CDS) if the particular asset defaults. Buyer of CDS makes a series of payments (the CDS &amp;ldquo;fee&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;spread&amp;rdquo;) to the seller and, in exchange, may expect to receive a payoff if the asset defaults.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if a lender is worried that a borrower is going to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/default2.asp&#34;&gt;default&lt;/a&gt; on a loan, the lender could use a CDS to offset or swap that risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So it is basically an insurance contract. I’m a lender, I’m worried my borrower is going to default, so I buy CDS from another investor (I pay periodic premiums), and I get reimbursed if the borrower does in fact default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credit default swaps are customized between the two counterparties involved, which makes them opaque, illiquid, and hard to track for regulators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I.e., you’d make a loan to someone, or you’d buy their debt…and at the same time, you’d also buy CDS on them, in order to hedge your risk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/summarizing-russ-roberts-gambling-with-other-peoples-money/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Notes on Hayek&#39;s &#34;The Pretense of Knowledge&#34; (1974)</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/notes-on-hayeks-the-pretense-of-knowledge-1974/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 19:02:39 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/notes-on-hayeks-the-pretense-of-knowledge-1974/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/notes-on-hayeks-the-pretense-of-knowledge-1974/ -&lt;p&gt;Key Takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“men’s fatal striving to control society—a striving which makes him not only a tyrant over his fellows, but which may well make him the destroyer of a civilization which no brain has designed but which has grown from the free efforts of millions of individuals.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No knowledge &amp;gt; some “knowledge” if it forces you to act with some humility and avoid decisions with big, unintended, difficult-to-reverse, negative consequences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gardener &amp;gt; Craftsman, when it comes to social order. Gardeners cultivating an environment for plants, not like a craftsman shaping his handiwork. [You don’t need to understand the details of photosynthesis in order to have a beautiful gardener.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key question: When trying to influence an outcome, are you able to observe all the factors that may influence that outcome? If not, you might not like what you find when you try to influence that outcome. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recent example where I see all this playing out in current affairs: &lt;a href=&#34;https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/11/21/contra-robinson-on-public-food/&#34;&gt;Nixon-era effort to increase food production&lt;/a&gt; towards stamping out hunger led to the subsidization of corn and Big Farming and the creation of high-fructose corn syrup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the scientistic error?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“mechanical and uncritical application of habits of thought to fields different from those in which they have been formed”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why don’t methods from the physical sciences work when applied to influencing the social order?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Short answer: relative complexity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the social sciences:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“the aspects of the events to be accounted for about which we can get quantitative data are necessarily limited and may not include the important ones. ”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“in the social sciences often that is treated as important which happens to be accessible to measurement.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whereas, in physical sciences:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“any important factor which determines the observed events will itself be directly observable and measurable”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes the physical sciences different from the social sciences?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher penalty for over-confidence (talking about people’s lives)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complexity
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“structures whose characteristic properties can be exhibited only by models made up of relatively large numbers of variables. Competition, for instance, is a process which will produce certain results only if it proceeds among a fairly large number of acting persons.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In particular, &lt;em&gt;organized&lt;/em&gt; complexity
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“character of the structures showing it depends not only on the properties of the individual elements of which they are composed, and the relative frequency with which they occur, but also on the manner in which the individual elements are connected with each other.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impact of scientistic error?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broadly: Making huge decisions based on a not just imperfect but necessarily distorted and biased view of reality
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[unknowable facts/data that] “cannot be confirmed by quantitative evidence…are simply disregarded by those sworn to admit only what they regard as scientific evidence: they thereupon happily proceed on the fiction that the factors which they can measure are the only ones that are relevant.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Counterproductive [inflationary?] policy
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“assertion that there exists a simple positive correlation between total employment and the size of the aggregate demand…belief that we can permanently assure full employment by maintaining total money expenditure at an appropriate level.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the chief cause of unemployment, to Hayek?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“discrepancies between the distribution of demand among the different goods and services and the allocation of labor and other resources among the production of those outputs.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impact of &amp;ldquo;scientistic&amp;rdquo; policies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efforts to engineer the way to equilibrium (and subsequently full employment) end up backfiring, because you can’t know the equilibrium price in the first place. And by intervening, you end up making it harder for the market to get to equilibrium:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“the increase of aggregate demand [has] become a cause of a very extensive misallocation of resources which is likely to make later large-scale unemployment inevitable”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Hayek, why didn&amp;rsquo;t most economists see it this way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bias to use only directly observable/quantitatively measurable magnitude or phenomena&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://mises.org/library/pretense-knowledge&#34;&gt;https://mises.org/library/pretense-knowledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/notes-on-hayeks-the-pretense-of-knowledge-1974/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Reaction to Emily Wilson’s The Odyssey, Wonder and Education</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/reaction-to-emily-wilsons-the-odyssey-wonder-and-education/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 21:38:25 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/reaction-to-emily-wilsons-the-odyssey-wonder-and-education/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/reaction-to-emily-wilsons-the-odyssey-wonder-and-education/ -&lt;p&gt;How I picked it up: Tyler Cowen named it his &lt;a href=&#34;https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2018/11/best-book-2018.html&#34;&gt;best book of 2018&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tyler called this a “joy to read” and praised Wilson’s introductory essay. I agree with this assessment, and I’ll add to this by singling out Wilson’ Translator’s Note, which I think is the book’s hidden gem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I was eight years old, my primary school put on a production of a (much-shortened) &lt;em&gt;Odyssey&lt;/em&gt;, complete with costumes, song, and dance…It was a turning point in my life. I was enthralled by the production, not only because we could pretend to gouge out the headmaster’s eye (thrilling though that was), or just because I was cast to play a goddess (ditto), but because of the story and the atmosphere it evoked: a world of magic and adventure, of diverse cultures (both human and nonhuman, welcoming and murderous, foreign and familiar), and of an individual’s struggle to survive and return home. After this experience, I was inspired to read as many Greek myths as I could find…Over the decades since my eight-year old performance, &lt;em&gt;The Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; has always been with me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt; is a proper basis for picking up and sticking to a book!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This anecdote reminded me of one of my favorite childhood memories. This was probably 1st grade. My school music teacher played us some impressionist classical music. Think it was Debussy. We were lying down with eyes closed, and then up on our feet playing to the music. I think she basically asked us to free-associate what the music brought to mind. I recall volunteering something about meandering through the Milky Way or walking on the moon, and my teacher’s enthusiasm at what I’d shared. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading a book ought to be joyful, imaginative and &lt;a href=&#34;https://meaningness.com/wonder&#34;&gt;wonderful&lt;/a&gt;, or else abandoned. Speaking from my own experience, I think this dimension isn’t sufficiently prioritized when &lt;em&gt;The Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; is “taught” in school - as if the richest components of experiencing a book could be taught from the top-down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I though this was a great book. But the way “classics” are put on a pedestal tends to backfire. They are made to seem just so damn serious and important. Which is quite the opposite of the attitude that will make reading a book like this useful - i.e. - &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other day, a friend of mine sent me &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hFZFjoX2cGg&#34;&gt;a delightful video&lt;/a&gt; from a engineer-YouTuber playing a high-tech game with the squirrels in his backyard. His initial goal was to save his new bird feeder from the squirrels, but quickly evolved into exploration of squirrels’ ingenuity and the physics of their quirky capabilities. His enthusiasm and delight for his work is infectious. Quite similar to the vibe of Wilson’s translator’s note. I can imagine he had some similarly wonderful experiences tinkering around as a kid. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction and tension between fuzzy and techie, or between great books or whatever else a kid might want to read or do, ultimately misses the point. Education ought to prioritize a commitment to playfulness and wonder across, or independent of, academic disciplines. Playfulness and wonder are the “super” qualities. And maybe this is something that education shouldn’t accomplish by trying to do more, but by simply doing less (via negativa) and allowing more space for kids to pursue what they find wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that I’m still wondering about is why this ought to be considered “one of the greatest works of political thought.” I certainly don’t find Odysseus’ example instructive. He survives and persists and accomplishes his goals. He is cunning and effective. But all his men die! Hardly worthy of admiration. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I’m happy to let this be a wonderful and ridiculous story that’s best not taken so seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/reaction-to-emily-wilsons-the-odyssey-wonder-and-education/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Something like political economy</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/intro_political_economy/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/intro_political_economy/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/intro_political_economy/ -&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been an avid reader/listener of Marginal Revolution, EconTalk, Conversations with Tyler, and Nassim Nicholas Taleb&amp;rsquo;s works for a few years now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a handful of great classes at Stanford covering related subjects: &amp;ldquo;History of Capitalism&amp;rdquo; with Jennifer Burns, &amp;ldquo;American Economic History&amp;rdquo; with Gavin Wright, &amp;ldquo;The Relations Between Philosophical Enquiry and Historical Enquiry&amp;rdquo; with Rahul Chaudhri, and &amp;ldquo;Capitalism and its Discontents&amp;rdquo; with Sean Hanretta and J.P. Daughton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read Niall Ferguson, Jonathan Levy, Albert Hirschman and Emma Rothschild books in my free time. I wrote a history thesis exploring the political ramifications of information technologies, as foreseen in the 60&amp;rsquo;s by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Baran&#34;&gt;Paul Baran&lt;/a&gt;. (Really, it was a political economy essay masquerading as a history thesis.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to more deliberately learn and explore the intersections of history, economics and philosophy for a while. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as it so often happens, I didn&amp;rsquo;t need much help in the &amp;ldquo;how&amp;rdquo; department. Mainly I just needed a little encouragement&amp;hellip;that such an endeavor might be both possible and fruitful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Russ Roberts hit the nail on the head in &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/EconTalker/status/1258420028426387458&#34;&gt;a series of tweets&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago. Some excerpts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Option B is to read deeply in the ideas of Smith and Hayek&amp;ndash;emergent order, the power of specialization, non-mathematical theories of growth&amp;ndash;gaining an appreciation for the imperfections of markets and how decentralized trial and error by entrepreneurs using local knowledge yield improvements in standard of living not easily captured in equations. The imperfections of both private and public processes to improve the lot of humanity is discussed. The courses on statistics lean heavily on the insights of Nassim Nicholas Taleb&amp;hellip;Option A is a dumbed down version of graduate economics training. Option B is something else, something that is available today in a partial version at best in only a handful of places&amp;hellip;Some places have something like this called something like political economy&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s time to order off the menu! Today I start &amp;ldquo;Option B,&amp;rdquo; and I&amp;rsquo;ll be writing and musing here and on Twitter as I go.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll try to summarize, connect the dots, lay out &lt;a href=&#34;https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2019/07/how-i-practice-at-what-i-do.html&#34;&gt;differing points of view&lt;/a&gt;, and investigate how what I&amp;rsquo;m reading informs my view of current affairs. I&amp;rsquo;m particularly interested in the issue of &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/8vc-news/capture-the-flag-7b4abffdd5d3&#34;&gt;crony capitalism&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/incerto/corporate-socialism-the-government-is-bailing-out-investors-managers-not-you-3b31a67bff4a&#34;&gt;corporate socialism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in Option B, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear from you&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/intro_political_economy/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>My favorite writing guidance</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/writing_guidance/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/writing_guidance/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/writing_guidance/ -&lt;h2 id=&#34;david-barnetthttpswwwtheguardiancombooksbooksblog2017apr05do-two-unpublished-books-make-you-a-failed-author-no-youre-a-quitter&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/booksblog/2017/apr/05/do-two-unpublished-books-make-you-a-failed-author-no-youre-a-quitter&#34;&gt;David Barnett&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dear Anonymous, you&amp;rsquo;re not a failure. You&amp;rsquo;re a quitter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;zadie-smithhttpswwwtheguardiancombooks2018jan21zadie-smith-you-ask-the-questions-self-doubt&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2018/jan/21/zadie-smith-you-ask-the-questions-self-doubt&#34;&gt;Zadie Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was asked, &amp;ldquo;Do you have any secret techniques for overcoming self-doubt?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She replied: &amp;ldquo;As you know, there isn&amp;rsquo;t really any solution to self-doubt. In the end, you just have to write and doubt simultaneously.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;richard-osmanhttpswwwtheguardiancombooks2020may02struggling-to-read-or-write-how-to-be-creative-in-lockdown&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2020/may/02/struggling-to-read-or-write-how-to-be-creative-in-lockdown&#34;&gt;Richard Osman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;But then I made a deal with myself, and you will need to make this deal too. I chose to ignore the doubting voice for a month. Just one month. I made myself sit down for two hours a day and write. For me it was 1,000 words at a time. I didn&amp;rsquo;t go back and revise the previous day&amp;rsquo;s work. I didn&amp;rsquo;t fuss over the opening sentence. I wrote 20,000 words in that month, and, honestly, at that point there was no turning back. My story existed, my characters existed, and I had a routine I knew I could stick to.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;alex-dancohttpsalexdancocom20191005five-writing-tips&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://alexdanco.com/2019/10/05/five-writing-tips/&#34;&gt;Alex Danco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t think you need to write every day. Some days your writing brain is off and that&amp;rsquo;s fine. But you need to ship something every week.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Never start with a blank page. Start with &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;. It could be an outline, it could be starting with quotes or excerpts from what other people have said about your topic or even an adjacent one. It could be &amp;ldquo;I want to make this point, and here&amp;rsquo;s why.&amp;rdquo; It could be &amp;ldquo;here are three people who I hope get something out of this, and why.&amp;rdquo; It doesn&amp;rsquo;t even have to be text: &lt;a href=&#34;http://email.mg2.substack.com/c/eJwlUMuOwyAQ-5pya8SzDQcOXUX9jYjAJEUlEAHpbv5-IZUQM3isMbbRBZaYDrXFXNCeIY3OKsL4TQhkFbekFz1yeZwTwKqdVyXtgLZ98s7o4mJo_P5GGXopgbEBexezpFzftWEYwzRzZmiv5cxn1ERGvVsHwYCCD6QjBkBevUrZ8oU9LvRZj_bwZ3UwsTNxrW-KiawFi3a1zsT4dmG56nzV1_rnjzNQYeRUoxKMb4RjIUhHumEYnj9YCkHvg2BPeeF4XWiX9ykXbd5NASWV9-B8l3TsJKuMpTk9R9XoWOta5-UYIejJg_1mUL6ZnZ7KsYEK8Js9lALpC55B9oxIVNVsrDuDOm39A44Lezg&#34;&gt;one trick&lt;/a&gt; I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://email.mg2.substack.com/c/eJwlkMGOhCAMhp9muGlAwMEDh92YeQ2DUGfIIrhQd9e3X3SSpg1t-dt-1iA8Uz70lgqSvUCevNOMi15K4rRwTElFfJmWDLAaHzTmHci2z8Fbgz7Fs1_1HScvTRcmZqaG--Isu_ecCymMUlIoNShme3IOmczuPEQLGn4gHykCCfqFuJUb_7h1j2omwJ8z0abWprW-O8qGGujpOlldBFyC_2uqnj93MKEp1mTr8WhMdA2-oMngmu8dIJYmGwv1F_H6VGKU9kxQKVnL2nEcH590kLK7j5I_hpug67Nryz4XNPbrXIBkXfboQ5tNagdeO54niKtUOUw1rrWOxwTRzAHcGxG-kV4n47GBjvBbAiBCficvzoqzgdRpLlXNqK-r_wETxoYk&#34;&gt;pretty often&lt;/a&gt; is grabbing screenshots of tweets and throwing them into my Evernote doc. You can get rid of all of this later, although you may realize you want to keep it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;james-clearhttpsjamesclearcom3-2-1january-16-2020&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jamesclear.com/3-2-1/january-16-2020&#34;&gt;James Clear&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;3 tips for getting started as a writer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Publish on a schedule. Consistency develops ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Share your writing publicly. Writing is a magnet. It attracts like-minded people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. Write about what fascinates you. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to be an expert. Curiosity leads to expertise.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;morgan-houselhttpswwwcollaborativefundcomblogselfish-writing&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/selfish-writing/&#34;&gt;Morgan Housel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Good writers don&amp;rsquo;t walk around all day with 100,000 words of eloquent wisdom in their heads. No one can do that. They take some vague feeling they&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about, dig into a bunch, write down what they&amp;rsquo;ve discovered, realize half of it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense, delete most of it, write some more, realize the new stuff contradicts itself, panic when they realize they don&amp;rsquo;t understand the topic as well as they thought they did, talk to other smart people about why that is, learn something new that reminds them of this other thing that might tie into the second paragraph, discover that this thing they believed before they started writing isn&amp;rsquo;t actually true, realize that if that thing isn&amp;rsquo;t true then this other thing is probably really important, and so on endlessly. Grinding through this process reveals bits of context that are hopefully new discoveries to the reader. More importantly, they were likely new discoveries to the writer before they set out writing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Many of the good writers you enjoy probably aren&amp;rsquo;t much smarter than you. They&amp;rsquo;ve just forced themselves through the process of transferring vague feelings into words and the clarity that generates. The takeaway for voracious readers is that you can discover new perspectives and new context by writing yourself.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;david-perellhttpswwwperellcomblogthe-ultimate-guide-to-writing-online&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perell.com/blog/the-ultimate-guide-to-writing-online&#34;&gt;David Perell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s the best way to learn faster, build your resume, and find peers and collaborators who can create job and business opportunities for you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Content builds on itself. It multiplies and compounds.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Good news: You already have the tools to write online&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.writeofpassage.school/&#34;&gt;.&lt;/a&gt; You know how to read and write. And you have access to the Internet, which means you can create and distribute your work to the whole world at a low cost.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;byrne-hobarthttpsmarkermediumcomthe-marker-guide-to-content-marketing-for-non-hucksters-e0572916e217&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://marker.medium.com/the-marker-guide-to-content-marketing-for-non-hucksters-e0572916e217&#34;&gt;Byrne Hobart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Write for yourself, and you&amp;rsquo;ll write for the close friends you didn&amp;rsquo;t know you had.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;write about what you&amp;rsquo;re interested in, meet people you&amp;rsquo;d find interesting, discover your next topic, continue. The end result is that you subject your intellectual development to a sort of intelligent design instead of random evolution: you&amp;rsquo;ll tend to go where the next insights are.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;This means that anyone who writes about obsessions is helping to shelve, organize, and expand humanity&amp;rsquo;s library of useful knowledge. If you can do it, and do it well, you&amp;rsquo;re making the world a better place.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gleb-posobinhttpsthreaderappthread1091156574993870849&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://threader.app/thread/1091156574993870849&#34;&gt;Gleb Posobin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Your own ideas mostly seem trivial to you because you have the right concept structures in place to support them. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t come up with these ideas otherwise. So it&amp;rsquo;s easier to notice your own ideas in a dialogue: your friend has different concept structures and notices them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Corollary: don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to say obvious things.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Corollary 2: it is ok if it seems to you that you do not have nontrivial ideas of your own. It is just hard to notice them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;patrick-mckenziehttpstwittercompatio11status936615043126370306&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/patio11/status/936615043126370306&#34;&gt;Patrick McKenzie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Meta thought: you radically underestimate both a) how much you know that other people do not and b) the instrumental benefits to you of publishing it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/writing_guidance/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 