<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>political economy on Sunil Rao</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/tags/political-economy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in political economy on Sunil Rao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 14:43:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/tags/political-economy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>WIP study guide #1: takeaways from “Political Economy 101”</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/takeaways-from-political-economy-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 14:43:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/takeaways-from-political-economy-101/</guid>
      <description>A few months ago, I set out to give myself an introduction to “something like” political economy. It was a conveniently vague way to assemble a reading plan around some things I’d been wanting to read for a while at the intersection of philosophy, economics, history and technology.
Though a bit scattered, doing this surfaced a few distinct topics and questions for me to pursue in future:
1. Epistemology, or the “theory of knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It’s Time to Play</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/its-time-to-play/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 02:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/its-time-to-play/</guid>
      <description>If today’s toys are tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s tech, then we must also start to play. Building on Marc Andreesen’s landmark essay, Tanner Greer identifies the source of our inability to build in recent cultural and social changes. A culture that seeks to solve problems by persuading and deferring to authorities, as we seem to do now - rather than through individual or collective self-reliance, as we used to in this country - will not build.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trade globally, love locally.</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/trade-globally-love-locally/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 22:28:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/trade-globally-love-locally/</guid>
      <description>A short summary of Russ Roberts&amp;rsquo; How Adam Smith Can Change Your Life Self-interest and incentives are how we take care of people we don’t know and organize large-scale systems. This is the subject matter of the Wealth of Nations. But we must also practice virtue, conscience, warmth, dignity, nobility amongst our inner circles in order to live a good life. This is the subject of the Theory of Moral Sentiments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build Local Soccer</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/build-local-soccer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 20:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/build-local-soccer/</guid>
      <description>We don’t just tune into the Premier League for the highest-quality soccer. Or for the fantastic coverage team at NBC. Or even for Kyle Martino’s earring.
We also tune in so that we can take part in European soccer culture. It’s the pageantry, the songs, the chants, the pasty-faced British guys who just got out of the same pre-match pub their grandfathers went to. All these mark a sense of tradition, loyalty between club and community, and community ownership of the the club - if not in financial or legal terms, than at least in spirit - that predate big-time commercialization of the sport.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yes-and political economy: notes on Breaking Smart, Season 1.</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/yes-and-political-economy-notes-on-breaking-smart-season-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 19:18:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/yes-and-political-economy-notes-on-breaking-smart-season-1/</guid>
      <description>Ride the software wave or cling to a sinking ship
Software is a rare general-purpose soft technology (writing, money) that is transforming, upending the industrial social order, creating dramatic win-lose situations based on who appreciates and gets on the right side of its impact.
We’re just at the beginning - infra has only just gotten in place for deployment, it operates under other labels (e.g. genomics innovation driven by software), and has been driven by politically non-confrontational youth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A very (very very) short introduction to socialism</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/a-very-very-very-short-introduction-to-socialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 19:05:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/a-very-very-very-short-introduction-to-socialism/</guid>
      <description>My notes on the first section of OUP&amp;rsquo;s Socialism: A Very Short Introduction, which covers socialism&amp;rsquo;s various theories and traditions The general idea Commitment to the creation of an egalitarian society (equality of resources, rights, opportunities). That inheritance of capital/wealth provides a few with immense privilege; meanwhile, a cycle of deprivation limits opportunities and influence for the rest. Ergo, private property prevents any hope of equality. Optimistic view of human beings’ willingness to cooperate with one other on large scale.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Under the yoke of growth: Timothy Shenk&#39;s essay, &#34;Apostles of Growth&#34;</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/under-the-yoke-of-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 21:44:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/under-the-yoke-of-growth/</guid>
      <description>Summary and takeaways from the Timothy Shenk essay in The Nation. Historians of capitalism describe the discovery of deliberate economic growth its consequences. They chronicle the operations of the “relentless logic of capitalism,” and how growth has became (and remains) our master at the expense of a commitment to justice.
The point that growth has become our master seems true to me. At company-level and federal level, we seem to contort ourselves and our environments to show growth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is political freedom limited by economic freedom? Notes on Hayek&#39;s &#34;The Road to Serfdom.&#34;</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/is-political-freedom-limited-by-economic-freedom-notes-on-hayeks-the-road-to-serfdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 18:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/is-political-freedom-limited-by-economic-freedom-notes-on-hayeks-the-road-to-serfdom/</guid>
      <description>2-sentence summary: Socialism is incompatible with freedom. It leads to fascism and dictatorship.
Observations and avenues for further investigation I wonder if Hayek mischaracterizes the socialist/egalitarian view on economic freedom and its relation to political freedom…If he underestimates the importance of / extent to which society must go to support every individual’s economic freedom in order to assure political freedom. Socialism seems &amp;ldquo;nice.&amp;rdquo; We get to bathe in our good intentions, celebrate our niceness and shared values.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CBT for economic history: Albert Hirschman on &#34;Political Economics and Possibilism&#34;</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/cbt-for-economic-history-albert-hirschman-on-political-economics-and-possibilism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 21:32:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/cbt-for-economic-history-albert-hirschman-on-political-economics-and-possibilism/</guid>
      <description>Summary We tend to be short-sighted, impractical and overly pessimistic interpreters and agents of change. The search for (and the assumption that there exist) general laws whose continuous unfolding explains change over time can backfire. By passing history through his “possibilist” filters, Hirschman “[defends] the right to a nonprojected future as one of the truly inalienable rights of every person and nation.” How this squares with other perspectives: This squares nicely with Taleb’s view that “we are better at doing than explaining” and his low opinion of the “Soviet-Harvard complex,” as well as with Hayek’s talk of “man’s fatal striving to control society.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summarizing Russ Roberts&#39; &#34;Gambling with Other People&#39;s Money&#34;</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/summarizing-russ-roberts-gambling-with-other-peoples-money/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 14:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/summarizing-russ-roberts-gambling-with-other-peoples-money/</guid>
      <description>Summary The government bailed out debt-holders in a series of bank failures in the 70&amp;rsquo;s through the 90&amp;rsquo;s, signaling an implicit guarantee of creditors. This implicit guarantee combined with a politician-driven effort starting in the 90’s to orchestrate an increase in homeownership led to excessive use of leverage by Wall Street and aspiring homeowners to finance increasingly risky investments in housing in the 00&amp;rsquo;s. This in turn allowed Wall Street and politicians to privatize gains ($$, votes) and socialize eventual losses to taxpayers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Hayek&#39;s &#34;The Pretense of Knowledge&#34; (1974)</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/notes-on-hayeks-the-pretense-of-knowledge-1974/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 19:02:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/notes-on-hayeks-the-pretense-of-knowledge-1974/</guid>
      <description>Key Takeaways:
“men’s fatal striving to control society—a striving which makes him not only a tyrant over his fellows, but which may well make him the destroyer of a civilization which no brain has designed but which has grown from the free efforts of millions of individuals.” No knowledge &amp;gt; some “knowledge” if it forces you to act with some humility and avoid decisions with big, unintended, difficult-to-reverse, negative consequences Gardener &amp;gt; Craftsman, when it comes to social order.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something like political economy</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/intro_political_economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/intro_political_economy/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been an avid reader/listener of Marginal Revolution, EconTalk, Conversations with Tyler, and Nassim Nicholas Taleb&amp;rsquo;s works for a few years now.
I took a handful of great classes at Stanford covering related subjects: &amp;ldquo;History of Capitalism&amp;rdquo; with Jennifer Burns, &amp;ldquo;American Economic History&amp;rdquo; with Gavin Wright, &amp;ldquo;The Relations Between Philosophical Enquiry and Historical Enquiry&amp;rdquo; with Rahul Chaudhri, and &amp;ldquo;Capitalism and its Discontents&amp;rdquo; with Sean Hanretta and J.P. Daughton.
I read Niall Ferguson, Jonathan Levy, Albert Hirschman and Emma Rothschild books in my free time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
