<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Uncategorized on A Hugo Site</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/tags/uncategorized/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Uncategorized on A Hugo Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This is a customized copyright.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 04:04:51 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/tags/uncategorized/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hopelessly half-baked study guide #3: The Kegan Model</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/hopelessly-half-baked-study-guide-3-the-kegan-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 04:04:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/hopelessly-half-baked-study-guide-3-the-kegan-model/</guid>
      <description>Several friends and mentors of mine have suffered the misfortune of lending me their ears during my Kegan phase. For the uninitiated, Robert Kegan has proposed a fascinating and encouraging model of psychological development that continues well into adulthood - which, one learns, was not previously generally accepted. This is sort of a cheat-post - I repurpose what I wrote from an email exchange my attempt (only what I wrote) to put Kegan’s work in my words and reflect on it’s applicability, lightly edited for clarity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“How to Do What You Love” needs a prequel</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/how-to-do-what-you-love-needs-a-prequel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 01:29:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/how-to-do-what-you-love-needs-a-prequel/</guid>
      <description>“To do something well you have to like it,” Paul Graham famously wrote. This advice can come like a friendly slap in the face. Of course! Striving to excel in a domain that does not interest us is obviously silly. But are we capable of liking something long enough - and without grasping at it and suffocating it - to do it well?
Some thoughts from others:
Andrew Yang: “They need status and reassurance…They think in two years, not 20.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hopelessly half-baked study guide #2: Classical Antiquity...</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/blasphemously-brief-guide-1-classical-antiquity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 22:00:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/blasphemously-brief-guide-1-classical-antiquity/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;the Greco-Roman world, centered on the Mediterranean, of the 8th century BC and the 6th century AD. Why is the classical antiquity period significant?
Western civilization - modernity - was born of a mix of the classical and the Christian. And the recent history of the world - for the last several hundred years, until recently - has been the history of westernization or modernization of the whole world: scientific ideas/methods, new ways of thinking, military technology, and public administration fueling greater power and wealth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hopelessly half-baked study guide #1: takeaways from “Political Economy 101”</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/takeaways-from-political-economy-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 14:43:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/takeaways-from-political-economy-101/</guid>
      <description>A few months ago, I set out to give myself an introduction to “something like” political economy. It was a conveniently vague way to assemble a reading plan around some things I’d been wanting to read for a while at the intersection of philosophy, economics, history and technology.
Though a bit scattered, doing this surfaced a few distinct topics and questions for me to pursue in future:
1. Epistemology, or the “theory of knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The link between antitrust and inequality</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/the-link-between-antitrust-and-inequality-jonathan-teppers-the-myth-of-capitalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 16:11:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/the-link-between-antitrust-and-inequality-jonathan-teppers-the-myth-of-capitalism/</guid>
      <description>The Myth of Capitalism, by Jonathan Tepper In summary: Current, unacceptable levels of inequality stem from the deterioration of antitrust enforcement and the subsequent “toll road-ization” of the American economy. Mergers permitted without scrutiny, oligopoly proliferates; workers, customers, suppliers get squeezed. This deterioration was driven by revolving doors, cronyism, and Chicago economic philosophy. This is all exacerbated by concentrated ownership of these toll roads by the wealthy.
Questions &amp;amp; Review Tepper&amp;rsquo;s story is enticingly simple.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools for thought = mental bureaucracy?</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/tools-for-thought-mental-bureaucracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 17:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/tools-for-thought-mental-bureaucracy/</guid>
      <description>*This is a hot take, quite happy to be disagreed with and told why I&amp;rsquo;m wrong*
I think focusing on using tools for thought can easily turn into the construction of a suffocating educational bureaucracy. It’s utopian high-modernism applied to independent learning.
What if it’s better to just learn things that really makes us burn with curiosity and desire, that make us want to keep building on that foundation and go deeper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toni Morrison’s &#34;Sula&#34; &amp; playing with meaning</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/toni-morrisons-sula-playing-with-meaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 17:43:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/toni-morrisons-sula-playing-with-meaning/</guid>
      <description>This was my first Toni Morrison book, and it was magnificent. It is clear as you read it that a master is at work. You feel you are in the palm of her hand, and you like it that way.
Horrifying and painful yet life-affirming all at once. Dramatic but in a playful, deft way. Compassionate but not pitying. Pensive but not preachy or judgmental. Especially on this last note - this novel brought back to mind David Chapman’s schematic of predominant stances toward meaning.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
