<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>soccer on Sunil Rao</title>
    <link>http://sunilvrao.com/tags/soccer/</link>
    <description>Recent content in soccer on Sunil Rao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 01:56:11 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://sunilvrao.com/tags/soccer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Highlights that don&#39;t make the reel</title>
      <link>http://sunilvrao.com/post/highlights-that-dont-make-the-reel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2020 01:56:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sunilvrao.com/post/highlights-that-dont-make-the-reel/</guid>
      <description>The headlines after the 0-0 draw at Old Trafford were sadly predictable. “Man United, Chelsea show why Premier League title challenge is beyond them.”
My favorite shot from that game (though let’s be honest it didn’t have much competition…tehe) was of Thiago Silva and Edinson Cavani connecting after the final whistle. Silva puts his hand on his former teammate’s shoulder…you can imagine these guys have so much to talk about. The warmth is obvious. Both approaching the end of their playing careers, embarking on perhaps their final adventures at the elite level and, you’d imagine, plainly interested in how the other guy is doing and adjusting to his new situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build Local Soccer</title>
      <link>http://sunilvrao.com/post/build-local-soccer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 20:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sunilvrao.com/post/build-local-soccer/</guid>
      <description>We don’t just tune into the Premier League for the highest-quality soccer. Or for the fantastic coverage team at NBC. Or even for Kyle Martino’s earring.
We also tune in so that we can take part in European soccer culture. It’s the pageantry, the songs, the chants, the pasty-faced British guys who just got out of the same pre-match pub their grandfathers went to. All these mark a sense of tradition, loyalty between club and community, and community ownership of the the club - if not in financial or legal terms, than at least in spirit - that predate big-time commercialization of the sport.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
