<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Hugo Site</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on A Hugo Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This is a customized copyright.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 04:04:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Tools for thought = mental bureaucracy?</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/tools-for-thought-mental-bureaucracy/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 17:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/tools-for-thought-mental-bureaucracy/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/tools-for-thought-mental-bureaucracy/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*This is a hot take, quite happy to be disagreed with and told why I&amp;rsquo;m wrong*&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think focusing on using &lt;a href=&#34;https://numinous.productions/ttft/&#34;&gt;tools for thought&lt;/a&gt; can easily turn into the construction of a suffocating educational bureaucracy. It’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seeing_Like_a_State&#34;&gt;utopian high-modernism&lt;/a&gt; applied to independent learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if it’s better to just learn things that really makes us burn with curiosity and desire, that make us want to keep building on that foundation and go deeper. The subject matter itself, in combination with our lifestyles (work, or random observations) should provide plenty of motivation for us to keep digging - such that we naturally reinforce our learning without needing to plan or systematize the necessary reinforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not, then maybe either we should learn something else instead, or we need to change our lifestyles, our perspective and/or our capacity to appreciate! If you’re not doing things / running into situations in life that make use of what you’re learning and/or motivate further learning, then you have bigger problems then whether or not to read a textbook in order to learn the subject matter you apparently desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surrender to your curiosity. There’s a lot of knowledge out there, we want to grasp it. We feel unsafe and insecure and worry in response to all the things we don’t know. Get used to it! Now, if I can only take my own advice&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in Nassim Taleb’s &lt;em&gt;Incerto&lt;/em&gt;, he talks about his study of probability. While still a trader, after a long and stressful day he would study probability textbooks but put them down if/when they got boring. He kept going, onto the next one. He did not get in the way of his own natural curiosity. His job provided with plenty of impetus to learn, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[10/28 update: I mostly disagree with the above. The few enlightened beings among us are free to think and act appropriately, spontaneously. For the rest of us, we make do with what tools we have.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/tools-for-thought-mental-bureaucracy/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Build Local Soccer</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/build-local-soccer/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 20:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/build-local-soccer/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/build-local-soccer/ -&lt;p&gt;We don’t just &lt;a href=&#34;https://morningconsult.com/2019/08/28/global-is-cool-the-growing-appeal-of-premier-league-soccer-in-america/&#34;&gt;tune into the Premier League&lt;/a&gt; for the highest-quality soccer. Or for the fantastic coverage team at NBC. Or even for Kyle Martino’s earring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also tune in so that we can take part in &lt;em&gt;European soccer culture&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the pageantry, the songs, the chants, the pasty-faced British guys who just got out of the same pre-match pub their grandfathers went to. All these mark a sense of tradition, loyalty between club and community, and community ownership of the the club - if not in financial or legal terms, than at least in spirit - that predate big-time commercialization of the sport. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I think it’s precisely these “pre-commercial” qualities of European soccer that make it so attractive on this side of the pond. There is something on offer in European soccer culture that is magical and likely unfamiliar to those of us outside SEC or “Friday Night Lights” football country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoy watching the Premier League as much as anyone. I love that it provides instant common ground with someone from across the world. I love that you can go to bar on Saturday in New York City and see Arsenal and Tottenham fans getting into it come derby day. But it’s a little &lt;em&gt;lame&lt;/em&gt; - and I suspect in the long-term less rewarding - to follow European soccer without supporting and building up our own local soccer institutions. As Americans we’ll always be on the outside looking in at European soccer. By helping to build up our local soccer institutions, we can create the traditions that our own grandchildren might follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it has been exciting to see MLS teams - especially the likes of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cuAytnDGKMQ&#34;&gt;Atlanta United&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SFBUNbJLHro&#34;&gt;Portland Timbers&lt;/a&gt; - grow intensely popular in relatively short periods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I get the sense that MLS is trying to manufacture its own grassroots, scarf-bearing, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=USUFGnNHUTs&amp;amp;feature=emb_rel_end&#34;&gt;derby day mythology&lt;/a&gt; in order to compete for American fans of European soccer. And this rings a little phony to me. MLS is a centrally planned league of teams operated by wealthy investors from its inception. Wouldn’t you rather say you were a fan of a team started by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Arsenal_F.C._(1886%E2%80%931966)&#34;&gt;a bunch of munitions workers&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare the following two scenes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sunilvraocom.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/img_4514.jpg?w=1024&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2018 MLS Cup Playoffs, 2nd leg of the Eastern Conference Finals, Red Bull Arena. Red Bulls needed to overcome a 3-0 deficit to reach the MLS Cup Finals. They filled about 2/3 of the stadium before kick off.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sunilvraocom.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/img_4058.jpg?w=1024&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. FC Union Berlin’s first game of the 2018-2019 season in the German second division.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XXI6oWjlV8M&amp;amp;t=329s&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fans helped&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;this stadium.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sure MLS wants to see Red Bull Arena packed ahead of a big playoff game. But, especially in light of allegations of antitrust against MLS’ commercial business partner by another domestic league, I wonder if the rush to get soccer taken seriously in the U.S. from the ‘top-down’ inhibits sincere community ownership within the sport. &lt;em&gt;That’s&lt;/em&gt; what packs second division stadiums and prompts lovers of the game to look across the pond for soccer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Youthful companies like &lt;a href=&#34;https://awaydaysfootball.com&#34;&gt;Away Days&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://talismancaps.com&#34;&gt;Talisman Caps&lt;/a&gt; embody our hunger for a grassroots soccer culture of our own. While the pandemic threatens the survival of small clubs - along with anyone else lacking deep pockets - at the same time, it also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.detroitnews.com/story/sports/soccer/2020/07/30/niyo-detroit-city-fc-offers-piece-ownership-its-supporters/5545513002/&#34;&gt;catalyzes grassroots ownership&lt;/a&gt;. And perhaps, one day soon, our experience of the pandemic will motivate us to watch the beautiful game live and together in our local, physical communities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve been reminded by the pandemic that &lt;a href=&#34;https://a16z.com/2020/04/18/its-time-to-build/&#34;&gt;we need to build&lt;/a&gt;, that there are certain things we should not outsource. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add soccer culture to the list. Let’s not rely exclusively on getting it overseas. Let’s build local soccer like never before.&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/build-local-soccer/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Building win-win commercial gyms</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/building-win-win-commercial-gyms/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 20:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/building-win-win-commercial-gyms/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/projects/building-win-win-commercial-gyms/ -&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-premise&#34;&gt;The premise:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commercial gyms generally want you to buy a subscription and never use it. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ihrsa.org/about/media-center/press-releases/latest-ihrsa-data-over-6b-visits-to-39-570-gyms-in-2018/&#34;&gt;More than 70 million Americans&lt;/a&gt; had a gym membership last year, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.glofox.com/blog/10-gym-membership-statistics-you-need-to-know/&#34;&gt;only 18% went consistently&lt;/a&gt;. All 70 million paid an average of $58 per month for their membership. And if you do go - especially at a reasonable hour - the equipment you need could be occupied. We’re seriously still doing this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many, home/outdoor fitness does the job. Many of us are familiar with P90X or, more recently, things like Mirror, that require minimal equipment. And perhaps the pandemic will accelerate the trend towards non-gym fitness. Some may realize that they can do without the membership and prefer the savings and the safety of home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for others, home/outdoor fitness won’t suffice. A shared gym, or something like it, is still indispensable for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heavy shit. The stuff you lift to get strong. I’ll focus on barbell training, since those folks are the primary audience for this. You can’t do a barbell training program in an apartment. And unless you have the right space (e.g. garage or basement with high ceilings), can put ~$2000 towards a power rack with all accoutrements, and expect not to move in the foreseeable future, you can’t train with barbells anywhere else either.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not working out by yourself. Some of us appreciate working out amongst others doing the same, or we just like getting out, and places like gyms are good for serendipitous acquaintances. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: gyms are useful but, in their current version, often unsatisfying. Is there a better, software-enabled way forward?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;yes-on-demand-a-la-carte-equipment-software-could-turn-win-lose-dynamic-into-a-win-win-dynamic&#34;&gt;Yes: On-demand, a la carte equipment. Software could turn win-lose dynamic into a win-win dynamic.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Book the equipment you want. Pay only for what you use (e.g., squat rack for 30 minutes), at a price based on supply of and demand for desired equipment at the desired time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On-demand booking would give gyms a clear sense of what equipment people want, and when they want it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When consumers head to the squat rack on Wednesday at 6pm, find it busy, and move onto plan B, this “message” may get lost or otherwise fail to influence equipment selection. They may gripe and fume to themselves, but in the interest of getting home, they do a different workout and leave. Not that gyms would necessarily care much if the gripers were to speak up, since gyms make so much money on getting people to sign up without showing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think many people aren’t getting what they want, and gyms either don’t know or don’t care. But maybe there is a world, not too far away, in which gyms adjusted supply of equipment, or the price of using that equipment, according to demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d certainly pay more if I knew I could have a squat rack on Wednesdays at 6pm. Presumably gyms would take my money in exchange for this privilege. And if a dynamic price does its job as a signal of demand, maybe these gyms would get some more goddamn squat racks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gyms often make equipment purchasing decisions based on what will drive new (and unused) subscription sign ups, rather than what will get utilized and satisfy members that, you know, actually go to the gym. This is sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May be worth noting that the ‘campers’ - you know, the guys who get to the gym at 4 and stay for three hours - might be quite unhappy about this. For the same price as the rest of us schmucks, they’ve been getting primo access. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But with on-demand booking, the silent gripers - who I believe outnumber the campers - will finally get what they want, and gyms will be able to charge them for it. Win-win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;question-marks&#34;&gt;Question marks:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a gym, would you trade your “no-show revenues” to see how much more you can make from the silent gripers? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how big is this group of silent gripers, how much more are they willing to pay? What will it take for them to develop some class consciousness? :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there is a game-theory dimension here. If you’re a gym, and as long as your competitors rely on no-shows the same as you, there is no reason to change. If one gym in an area were to adopt the on-demand/a la carte model, the silent gripers and the no-shows would vote with their feet, and the rest of the market would have no choice but to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/YmZfaNmuPV-SQU9yPt9RmjHNbu_b45aKXDJcZBAXhw-Wqx0dpQgtBNsqycKplrD_2fPvEThcBF8jvw3fHikizibPFlaxbxrfVbbZ98GtQmWk8223ctZgL3526Z3NjL4rznxCYX91&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.figma.com/proto/ZCzsMBT3Qu6iWrPPzM0NVE/Gym-Equipment-Booking?node-id=20199%3A0&amp;amp;scaling=scale-down&#34;&gt;Click here to see the prototype&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/projects/building-win-win-commercial-gyms/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Yes-and political economy: notes on Breaking Smart, Season 1.</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/yes-and-political-economy-notes-on-breaking-smart-season-1/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 19:18:32 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/yes-and-political-economy-notes-on-breaking-smart-season-1/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/yes-and-political-economy-notes-on-breaking-smart-season-1/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ride the software wave or cling to a sinking ship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software is a rare general-purpose soft technology (writing, money) that is transforming, upending the industrial social order, creating dramatic win-lose situations based on who appreciates and gets on the right side of its impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re just at the beginning - infra has only just gotten in place for deployment, it operates under other labels (e.g. genomics innovation driven by software), and has been driven by politically non-confrontational youth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve previously been rewarded for our credentials, but now we are rewarded for what we make. Will you adapt or cling to a sinking ship?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it’s not just about you…similar to Tanner Greer’s point about needing a culture of building, breaking smart at the individual level is how we break smart as a society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amidst abundance, hacking beats planning + vision.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small teams of hackers, not planners, are shaping and inheriting the future by figuring out how to do more with less.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enhanced information availability and lowered friction can make any field hacker-friendly (e.g. forestry). Once a field becomes hacker-friendly, software begins to eat it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll slouch towards both consumer utopia (more for less, gradual improvement) as well as producer utopia (some fluid descendant of secure but stifling paycheck world and liberating but precarious world of free agency).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authoritarian high modernism leads to trainwrecks (Brasilia) or, when slow the authoritarianism, to stalled, expensive, corrupt trains (&lt;a href=&#34;http://healthcare.gov&#34;&gt;healthcare.gov&lt;/a&gt;?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software introduces abundance; low marginal cost to writing software. Given this abundance, yes-and”-style, practical, bricoleur hacking beats and replaces “stakeholder alignment.” The group navigates in the fruitful yet foggy direction of maximal interestingness without a “vision.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Release early, release often” is how hacking beats planning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software makes for more positive-sum, infinite games…while subverting the authoritarian-purist planner-types and their world order. And “just as the principle of rough consensus and running code creates great software, consumer surplus and spillover effects create great societies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utopianism leads to authoritarianism…and backfires&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we need to stand up against technology to prevent it destroying human values and livelihoods? Or do we need to champion certain problems, industries and solutions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stance holds onto a wishful hope that we can and should agree on which jobs, lifestyles are worth protecting and entrenching. Pursuing utopian visions are how the victors of particular historical finite games hope to secure their gains and rest indefinitely on their laurels and provide security/stability. But such totalitarian visions eventually collapse on themselves and make life a nightmare for out-groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Hmm this is a juicy point, I sense there are compelling counterarguments…e.g. if in the process of creating that consumer surplus/spillover, you end up creating monopolies that “scarcify” the easy access that the Internet made possible.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We face a society-wide condition of pastoral longing, and it comes in two flavors: luddite-nostalgia &amp;amp; flying-car/sputnik-ism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concern for technology-driven unemployment = elites wanting to rest on their laurels. We yearn for an Updated Old Thing (the next Sputnik moment).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the pastoral-ideal human is a high-IQ credentialist Organization Man, headed for gradual extinction, unable to compete with higher-IQ machines. The degenerate, breaking-smart humans of the software-eaten world on the other hand, have no such fears. They are too busy tinkering with new possibilities to bemoan imaginary lost utopias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We yearn for Keynes’ utopian society of leisure…but Keynes missed that with new lifestyles come new priorities, new lived values and new reasons to &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to work…the utopian leisure society was never coming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But…what about the truck drivers? Doesn’t embracing the Promethean path of progress require that there be something to support/tide over such people until new avenues of employment really emerge? And if we can’t agree on what/how to do this, will the Promethean path of progress get derailed? Couldn’t a people democratically choose to go in a pastoral direction? A large group of people who’ll be short-term hurt by the Promethean path would probably do all they could to prevent this…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two modern flavors are analogous to Jeffersonian and Hamiltonian visions. Jeffersonian vision of small-town agrarian life (blacks are the oppressed outgrip) collapses with Civil War (did the Jeffersonian model require slavery?), while Hamilton’s vision of manufacturing superpower would metastasize into military-industrial complex + too-big-to-fail economy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes me reconsider/nuance-up my reaction to Jayber Crow…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to square this with Chestertonian conservatism, and with Taleb-style…[ah but at least for the latter, I answer my own question…you don’t change anything. The point is about absence of authoritarianism, ability to execute utopian vision…unplanned developments can take place.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software enables moral progress. Beware your pastoralizing instinct.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It catalyzes a wider variety of lifestyles and more widespread agency. Moreover it allows you to do more with less and exercise agency - do/get what you want - without conflicting with others or needing power over others. Society can resolve conflicts - or avoid them in the first place - without need for authoritarian control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agency: not zero-sum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power: zero-sum (control over others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worried elites are a sign of progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tinkering beats and replaces the paradigm of goals &amp;amp; solutions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problems get solved “by accident” / indirectly through serendipitous, open-ended innovation. Goals, problems, solutions = authoritarian high-modernism. E.g. video conferencing vs. alternative energy re: carbon emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We harden around successful goal-driven strategies, usually creating extractive institutions that privilege a few and make it harder for us to adapt to a changing world. Goal-driven approach eventually exhausts itself, becomes unworkable (e.g. hard to do anything to address healthcare due to bureaucracy, ossified structure/intrenched interests, etc). Our efforts to “save” things often backfires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free people, free ideas, and accessible means of production makes for widespread tinkering &amp;amp; pluralism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finally own the means of production! Marx’s dream has come true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;locationlocationlocation —&amp;gt; connectionsconnectionsconnections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stream&lt;/em&gt;: open, inclusive, pluralist institutions; machine for serendipity, non-zero sum problem-solving and wealth-creation. Emerges when unrelated or conflicting worlds/networks collide. Work and play collide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helps to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; a serendipity-machine yourself…have feet in different worlds…usefulness of the useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soft technologies&lt;/em&gt;: ephemeral but embodied in a variety of specific physical forms. E.g., money is embodied by coins, writing embodied by a book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Breaking smart:&lt;/em&gt; an economic actor using early mastery of emerging technological leverage — in this case a young individual using software leverage — to wield disproportionate influence on the emerging future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;pivot&lt;/em&gt; allows the direction of development to change rapidly, without a detailed long-term plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Perpetual beta:&lt;/em&gt; serendipitous, empowering gap between running code and governing vision&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zemblanity:&lt;/em&gt; The opposite of serendipity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bHw4MMEnmpc&#34;&gt;Cf Roger Scruton on Why Beauty Matters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cf James Scott&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cf Taleb&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/yes-and-political-economy-notes-on-breaking-smart-season-1/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Introduce spaced repetition for more learning on Brilliant</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 18:04:07 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/ -&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/DyznVG0oAAWiHwyJh2Ps7L9BIPYRB-dFesdyTYno5IFCgTxtdTDk4eCMu4qhqgcJJUTUURiGgQ2UNAhWPtQ_sxzgF8LWHz9WupO1hdwvslwEnpdY0ddKzoOWl5tCVuav6FarCptc&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using Brilliant for a few weeks now. In the last few years, reading the works of Nassim Taleb on probability, randomness and complex systems rekindled my desire to learn probability and statistics. Instead of brushing off some rather dreary-looking textbooks in order to refresh my foundations, I decided to turn to Brilliant instead after stumbling upon its wonderful &lt;a href=&#34;https://brilliant.org/careers/&#34;&gt;culture page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emphasis on learning by doing has been refreshing. I appreciate that Brilliant provides instruction along the way instead of dumping it upfront. And I never fail to appreciate the reminders after I get a problem wrong…that without getting stumped, there is no learning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having used Brilliant a little bit, I had an idea for a new feature that might make it even better, and wanted to share that idea with you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduce-a-redo-protocol&#34;&gt;Introduce a “Redo Protocol”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-idea&#34;&gt;The Idea&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last spring I took a course through Manhattan Prep to prepare for the GMAT. If there was one thing my instructor made sure to drill into our heads, it was to prioritize our re-do log - to spend the _majority of our study tim_e redoing problems we’d previously gotten wrong rather than on doing new problems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea was this: You might for a short while understand the explanation for a problem you answered incorrectly, but you’d need to actually redo the problem - several times, over the course of a few weeks - in order to retrieve and, in so doing, internalize the new concept or approach such that you could apply recognize it or apply it in new situations. In other words, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.manhattanprep.com/gmat/blog/why-you-should-be-redoing-gmat-problems/&#34;&gt;you’d need to redo problems in order to &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Doing lots of new problems - without fully juicing them - was a trap. It would leave you wondering why your score had not improved despite dedicated effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructors at Manhattan Prep say that students who prioritized the redo log improved their scores much more. While this evidence is admittedly anecdotal, this is by no means a new or isolated observation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like Scott Young’s framework for the makeup of a good study routine. He names 5 key ingredients:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/oejVma2MaPIEipxLnxwryaQ8CrRYkRPF80X2vhiAI1V71wRVqdjI77r9XSa8XYzOZtEub57KvUA9BN8lUMJi6gfTbKRKrHtbZOrE6yNk2FgPEOvyWHVEpwhbm4_BUxPCQKrfPMZq&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/2020/06/30/perfect-studying-routine/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;scottyoung.com: “The Perfect Studying Routine.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Brilliant excels in “Instruction” (just what you need), “Retrieval” (emphasis on learning through doing over passive review) and “Feedback” (I find the explanations very helpful in general).*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By supporting “Spacing” (and “Retrieval”) through a redo protocol, Brilliant can make it easier for learners to execute the perfect study routine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;I didn’t address the “Understanding” component. Brilliant’s emphasis on learning through doing is the core component here. But I think Brilliant might get even better in the “Understanding” department by making it simpler for users to leverage&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://fs.blog/2012/04/feynman-technique/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;the Feynman technique&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;and/or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rubber duck debugging&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;within the fabric of each course.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-practice&#34;&gt;…in Practice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current “Saved” problems log provides the groundwork for a redo protocol. The main thing to add is the automatic reminders to redo it! That said, here are some specific things I&amp;rsquo;ve been chewing on that I think a good Redo Protocol might have or do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatically add any problem you get wrong to your redo log.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to add/remove problems to your redo log manually if you so choose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic reminders to redo these flagged problems; 2 days out, 1 week out, and 2 weeks out. [These specific checkpoints are a general idea. There may be some studies out there that offer suggestions, but also this could just be tested.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once you get it right [3]x in a row, it’s removed from the redo log.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatically reset the problem for you before you redo it, so you don’t accidentally see the explanation before your next attempt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you get the problem wrong again in the course of the redo’s, start from the beginning of the redo protocol: return to the problem 2 days, 1 week, 2 weeks later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give you credit in the system for redoing it (right now it looks like I haven’t done anything in Brilliant, even though I’ve done my redo’s offline).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourage you to write down a takeaway after viewing the explanation to a problem they’ve gotten wrong. E.g., what did you need to know in order to solve this problem? This is the first step towards cementing a new insight via active retrieval.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d want to play with how much to really build in the Redo Protocol into the fabric of the user experience. As I’ve described it above, it could feel a bit distinct from the courses themselves. I wouldn’t want this to feel like an added chore separate and on top of progressing in the course. To avoid this, maybe the user simply encounters problems from the/her Redo Log semi-randomly in the course of taking quizzes as currently designed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s all for now. I love what you all are doing, and look forward to seeing you grow!&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>A very (very very) short introduction to socialism</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/a-very-very-very-short-introduction-to-socialism/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 19:05:52 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/a-very-very-very-short-introduction-to-socialism/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/a-very-very-very-short-introduction-to-socialism/ -&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-notes-on-the-first-section-of-oups-_socialism-a-very-short-introduction_-which-covers-socialisms-various-theories-and-traditions&#34;&gt;My notes on the first section of OUP&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Socialism: A Very Short Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, which covers socialism&amp;rsquo;s various theories and traditions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-general-idea&#34;&gt;The general idea&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commitment to the creation of an egalitarian society (equality of resources, rights, opportunities). That inheritance of capital/wealth provides a few with immense privilege; meanwhile, a cycle of deprivation limits opportunities and influence for the rest. Ergo, private property prevents any hope of equality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimistic view of human beings’ willingness to cooperate with one other on large scale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emphasis community, cooperation and association; as compared to liberalism’s commitment to individualism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;origins&#34;&gt;Origins&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reaction to 19th-century urbanization and industrialization (coercion of workers, massive inequality).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;several-flavors-or-traditions&#34;&gt;Several ‘flavors’ or traditions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Utopianism: potential to develop a perfect, harmonious society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anarchism: complete opposition to the state…government is inherently oppressive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marxism: primarily defined by its view of political economy…that it was a matter of when, not if, capitalism collapsed. Focused on who owned the means of production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;marxs-theory-of-political-economy&#34;&gt;Marx’s theory of political economy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A business has two main inputs: constant capital (PP&amp;amp;E) and variable capital (labor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whereas in pre-capitalist societies the value of a product = amount of labor necessary to produce it, in capitalism the exchange value of labor &amp;lt; product that the labor created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Businesses increased profits by fighting labor power…it couldn’t change how much PP&amp;amp;E was required to produce $100 worth of goods, but it could try to reduce the wages sufficient to produce $100 worth of goods…i.e., leveraging each worker as much as it could&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eventually, as businesses fight labor power and invest in PP&amp;amp;E to increase productivity and profits, workers would be unable to afford goods that they helped produce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This would lead to cycles/crises of overproduction, consolidation and mass unemployment, eventually leading to the breakdown of the system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fundamental tension between laborers and owners of capital&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laborers (proletariat) would eventually overturn the social order and capture state power, which heretofore existed to serve the interests of the owners of capital &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;my-reaction-to-marxs-theory-of-political-economy&#34;&gt;My reaction to Marx’s theory of political economy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are producing goods using the resources of a firm, wouldn’t it make sense that the exchange value of labor &amp;lt; exchange value of the product? If you are a single craftsman, makes more sense that these two quantities would be equal. I.e., of course the firm is able to sell &amp;ldquo;your&amp;rdquo; work for more than you earn for it&amp;hellip;the final product is the sum of your labor and what the firm has added to it&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I do see this cycle of firms wanting to invest in technology in order to rely less on (expensive) labor…but two can play this game…workers can do things to increase their market power against firms, and if you assume this, no reason the game wouldn’t just go on continuously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If workers would eventually and forcefully take ownership of the means of production, would there ever come to be anything to own? (Don’t think so.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;communism&#34;&gt;Communism&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Centralized socialism, driven by a central ‘vanguard’ party (small group) leading the class war orchestrating the revolution in secretive and authoritarian fashion, instead of being led from the bottom-up by workers in democratic, popular fashion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is birthed by Lenin and the Bolsheviks who win the Russian Revolution ~1920&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communism and Social Democracy splinter from each other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;internal-axes-for-socialisms-different-flavors&#34;&gt;Internal axes for socialism’s different ‘flavors’&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tolerance for centralization vs democracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimism vs. pessimism on man’s interests (self vs. social) and ability to cooperate (follows the above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promise vs pessimism on the potential of human agency and planning ability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commitment to revolution vs reform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commitment to working-class internationalism vs nationalism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/a-very-very-very-short-introduction-to-socialism/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Under the yoke of growth: Timothy Shenk&#39;s essay, &#34;Apostles of Growth&#34;</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/under-the-yoke-of-growth/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 21:44:57 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/under-the-yoke-of-growth/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/under-the-yoke-of-growth/ -&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary-and-takeaways-from-the-timothy-shenk-essay-in-the-nationhttpswwwthenationcomarticlearchiveapostles-growth&#34;&gt;Summary and takeaways from the Timothy Shenk &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thenation.com/article/archive/apostles-growth/&#34;&gt;essay in The Nation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historians of capitalism describe the discovery of deliberate economic growth its consequences. They chronicle the operations of the “relentless logic of capitalism,” and how growth has became (and remains) our master at the expense of a commitment to justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point that growth has become our master seems true to me. At company-level and federal level, we seem to contort ourselves and our environments to show growth. But why should we dependent on growth to avoid collapse? This rings of Eric Weinstein’s comments about the “growth imperative.” Whether it’s because of technology, crony capitalism, inflationary policy, borrowing too much, borrowing from the young, borrowing from China…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond noting our fixation with growth, the historians of capitalism blame capitalism’s “relentless logic” for incredible injustices at the heart of the growth of the U.S. economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps an awareness that you have an income statement and a balance sheet makes you more likely to forget your humanity. But if, as Shenk points out, you don’t even need to be capitalist to apply relentless logic (USSR, China were largest producers of cotton by 1980), and if everything is capitalism’s fault…is &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; capitalism’s fault? Is capitalism really the fundamental operating force?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems to me like these historians of capitalism are looking for a singular boogeyman &amp;lsquo;force.&amp;rsquo; They practically anthropomorphize capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems to me that capitalism is not so much a fundamental force and more of a consequence of connectedness and scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, we live in a period where growth as we know it would be neither just, acceptable or sustainable. As &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1497533406/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1497533406&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=charleshughsm-20&#34;&gt;Charles Hugh Smith discusses&lt;/a&gt;, we need to be figuring out how to do more with less.&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/under-the-yoke-of-growth/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Is political freedom limited by economic freedom? Notes on Hayek&#39;s &#34;The Road to Serfdom.&#34;</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/is-political-freedom-limited-by-economic-freedom-notes-on-hayeks-the-road-to-serfdom/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 18:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/is-political-freedom-limited-by-economic-freedom-notes-on-hayeks-the-road-to-serfdom/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/is-political-freedom-limited-by-economic-freedom-notes-on-hayeks-the-road-to-serfdom/ -&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-sentence-summary&#34;&gt;2-sentence summary:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Socialism is incompatible with freedom. It leads to fascism and dictatorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;observations-and-avenues-for-further-investigation&#34;&gt;Observations and avenues for further investigation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wonder if Hayek mischaracterizes the socialist/egalitarian view on economic freedom and its relation to political freedom…If he underestimates the importance of / extent to which society must go to support every individual’s economic freedom in order to assure political freedom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Socialism seems &lt;a href=&#34;https://vividness.live/2011/06/10/nice-buddhism/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;nice.&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; We get to bathe in our good intentions, celebrate our niceness and shared values. Easy to imagine how this backfires.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigate to what extent Hayek’s framework holds up&amp;hellip;as it pertains to his argument that socialism really does end in fascism/dictatorship, and on the origins of monopoly. History as the laboratory to test the consequence of thought&amp;hellip;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would be interesting to compare to &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholars-stage.blogspot.com/2013/07/economies-of-scale-killed-american-dream.html&#34;&gt;T. Greer&lt;/a&gt; and Codevilla on “scale.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw out a timeline/chart out how the amount of scale has grown or diminished in a place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He frames this piece in &amp;ldquo;problem-ish&amp;rdquo; terms…there is an opponent, an enemy to be overcome. Who is framing the growth / exercise of freedom using language that highlights opportunity, rather than obstacle and adversary? Would that be useful? (cf Conscious Leadership.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;qa-style-notes&#34;&gt;Q&amp;amp;A-style notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the real intellectual fault line?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We all want to “employ systematic thinking in planning our affairs.” The dispute is more specifically about how planning is done, or who does it. 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I.e., should it be done my a central planner? Should the government “direct and organize all economic activities according to a ‘blueprint’, that is, ‘consciously direct the resources of society to conform to the planners’ particular views of who should have what’.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Or, should society “create conditions under which the knowledge and initiative of individuals are given the best scope so that they can plan most successfully.” &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is good planning? Is he simply advocating ‘moderate’ planning, or a middle ground?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No. You ‘plan’ only towards &lt;em&gt;ensuring&lt;/em&gt; competition. [Gardener vs. Craftsman.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why, theoretically, central planning leads to dictatorship&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You’ll find that if you plan by committee it won’t work very well, so power gets concentrated with individuals in order to get things done…slippery slope towards dictatorship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The more complex the world becomes, the more you will feel a lack of control, the more you will want to gain control over it…and this will backfire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decentralization especially important in a complex world&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The more complex the world becomes, the harder it is to coordinate activities centrally, the worse centralized planning will do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The origins of monopoly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not a necessary consequence of technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“The recent growth of monopoly is largely the result of a deliberate collaboration of organized capital and organized labour where the privileged groups of labour share in the monopoly profits at the expense of the community and particularly at the expense of those employed in the less well organized industries. However, there is no reason to believe that this movement is inevitable. The movement toward planning is the result of deliberate action. No external necessities force us to it.” &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Policy choices (presumably influenced by this nefarious collaboration)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important to assure basic economic security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“two kinds of security: the certainty of a given minimum of sustenance for all and the security of a given standard of life, of the relative position which one person or group enjoys compared with others.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Says society should guarantee basic economic security as well as comprehensive social insurance “for those common hazards of life against which few can make adequate provision.” [But not guarantee more than this.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key excerpts and notes on political freedom and economic freedom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Socialism was to bring ‘economic freedom’ without which political freedom was ‘not worth having’. “&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“To make this argument sound plausible, the word ‘freedom’ was subjected to a subtle change in meaning. The word had formerly meant freedom from coercion, from the arbitrary power of other men. Now it was made to mean freedom from necessity, release from the compulsion of the circumstances which inevitably limit the range of choice of all of us. Freedom in this sense is, of course, merely another name for power or wealth. The demand for the new freedom was thus only another name for the old demand for a redistribution of wealth.“&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“The economic freedom which is the prerequisite of any other freedom cannot be the freedom from economic care which the socialists promise us and which can be obtained only by relieving us of the power of choice. It must be that freedom of economic activity which, together with the right of choice, carries also the risk and responsibility of that right.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My response: Maybe the socialist/egalitarian argument is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; that political freedom isn’t worth having without first having economic freedom…it’s that you only have as much political freedom as you have economic freedom. I think that today’s egalitarian argument comes from the view that when there is tremendous inequality, and money provides political power, and you don’t have lots money, then you don’t have much of a voice and are thus less vulnerable to coercion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/is-political-freedom-limited-by-economic-freedom-notes-on-hayeks-the-road-to-serfdom/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Toni Morrison’s &#34;Sula&#34; &amp; playing with meaning</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/toni-morrisons-sula-playing-with-meaning/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 17:43:36 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/toni-morrisons-sula-playing-with-meaning/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/toni-morrisons-sula-playing-with-meaning/ -&lt;p&gt;This was my first Toni Morrison book, and it was magnificent. It is clear as you read it that a master is at work. You feel you are in the palm of her hand, and you like it that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horrifying and painful yet life-affirming all at once. Dramatic but in a playful, deft way. Compassionate but not pitying. Pensive but not preachy or judgmental. Especially on this last note - this novel brought back to mind David Chapman’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://meaningness.com/all-dimensions-schematic-overview&#34;&gt;schematic&lt;/a&gt; of predominant stances toward meaning. I think the lens of this schematic helped me to more deeply appreciate the novel. The intertwining of Nel and Sula’s lives is in a way the interplay of eternalist and nihilist-ish philosophies.&lt;/p&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/toni-morrisons-sula-playing-with-meaning/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>CBT for economic history: Albert Hirschman on &#34;Political Economics and Possibilism&#34;</title>
        <link>https://sunilvrao.com/post/cbt-for-economic-history-albert-hirschman-on-political-economics-and-possibilism/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 21:32:23 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/post/cbt-for-economic-history-albert-hirschman-on-political-economics-and-possibilism/</guid>
        <description>A Hugo Site https://sunilvrao.com/post/cbt-for-economic-history-albert-hirschman-on-political-economics-and-possibilism/ -&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We tend to be short-sighted, impractical and overly pessimistic interpreters and agents of change. The search for (and the assumption that there exist) general laws whose continuous unfolding explains change over time can backfire. By passing history through his “possibilist” filters, Hirschman “[defends] the right to a nonprojected future as one of the truly inalienable rights of every person and nation.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-this-squares-with-other-perspectives&#34;&gt;How this squares with other perspectives:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This squares nicely with Taleb’s view that “we are better at doing than explaining” and his low opinion of the “Soviet-Harvard complex,” as well as with Hayek’s talk of “man’s fatal striving to control society.” Though it seems Hirschman was a bit more optimistic of our potential to anticipate and leverage secondary reactions and consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;evidence&#34;&gt;Evidence:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most examples come from economic history, and this essay covers them at a high-level. I’d want to dig more into the specific examples to really believe him, but “possibilism” is a very compelling framework that I imagine I can also verify through experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One example that gets at how we fail to appreciate the interplay of economic and political motivators: Economists tend to assume the free-rider problem as a constant obstacle to supporting the public good. For which, taking action to address something - from the perspective of an individual - is a cost. But on certain occasions, as political scientists know, the story actually reverses. Taking action itself actually becomes a benefit, second only to having the desired result. [See next section for more examples)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-3-devices-or-filters-of-possibilism&#34;&gt;The 3 “devices” or “filters” of possibilism:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blessing (or curse) in disguise
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The presence of Native Americans ultimately proved an advantage to Anglo-Saxon settlers in North America. Whereas, uncontested open backlands in Brazil ultimately weakened European settlement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inverted (or disordered) causation
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protestant worth ethic didn’t cause entrepreneurialism…it arose from entrepreneurialism as a consequence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have the story that consensus / agreed-upon values cause democracy, or democracy arise from prolonged stand-off?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unintended consequences
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unintended consequences drive change (not just “wrought by the undeviatingly purposeful actions of some change agents.”)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change/evolution as a side effect of efforts to maintain status quo
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aside for the biology nerds: Legs evolved amongst the lungfish, which later evolved into the earliest amphibians, in order to get &lt;em&gt;back into the water&lt;/em&gt; in times of low water levels, and only much later did its descendants come to and stay ashore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Industrialization in many countries, particularly among the twentieth-century latecomers, was similarly brought underway not so much by the will to industrialize as by the need to keep up the supply of consumer goods whose importation became suddenly impossible during the world wars and the Great Depression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unintended consequences maintain stability/equilibrium
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free markets, Adam Smith…unintended consequence of everyone pursuing their own gain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voluntaristic / Unintended change are intertwined
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voluntaristic change may follow after unintended change has done the spadework&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;favorite-quote&#34;&gt;Favorite quote: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In the first place, the unintended change is often likely to be more revolutionary than change brought about by the most revolutionary of change agents, for the simple reason that the imagination of the change agent is severely limited by his immediate experience and historical precedent. More important, unintended change is of course far more difficult to detect and to block by the forces opposed to change; for that matter, these forces often participate unwittingly yet actively in bringing it about. On the other hand, unintended change may be less satisfying to those profiting from it than voluntaristic change, since it “falls into one’s lap” without either advance planning or sustained struggle.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-other-interesting-takeaways&#34;&gt;Some other interesting takeaways:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For students / observers of psychology and/or conscious leadership: In a nutshell, Hirschman is essentially applying CBT-cognitive restructuring, or the idea of “exploring the opposite,” to our understanding of change as a way to get “unstuck.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might not know it based on what’s going on in the news with respect to police brutality and BLM, but economics and activists might have something in common…Both may tend to be unwilling to settle for second-best outcomes or play with how they can leverage 2nd-order consequences or reactions (indirect means) that may ultimately be more powerful. Hirschman suggests that, as result, economists and activists are not as influential as they could be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A company can choose to “invest” in lobbying/political influence just like it invests in R&amp;amp;D. (I’d never thought about it quite this simply, but this makes perfect sense, especially given that we seem to a face a ‘crisis of growth’…political influence may be big companies’ best bet as fundamental innovation (arguably) declines and returns to other investment opportunities diminish. This could be an interesting thing to explore…how much &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; companies invest in political influence? Compare to R&amp;amp;D…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- https://sunilvrao.com/post/cbt-for-economic-history-albert-hirschman-on-political-economics-and-possibilism/ - This is a customized copyright.</description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 