<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>education on Sunil Rao</title>
    <link>https://sunilvrao.com/tags/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in education on Sunil Rao</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 02:27:11 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sunilvrao.com/tags/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>It’s Time to Play</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/its-time-to-play/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2020 02:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/its-time-to-play/</guid>
      <description>If today’s toys are tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s tech, then we must also start to play. Building on Marc Andreesen’s landmark essay, Tanner Greer identifies the source of our inability to build in recent cultural and social changes. A culture that seeks to solve problems by persuading and deferring to authorities, as we seem to do now - rather than through individual or collective self-reliance, as we used to in this country - will not build.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduce spaced repetition for more learning on Brilliant</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 18:04:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/projects/introduce-spaced-repetition-for-more-learning-on-brilliant/</guid>
      <description>I’ve been using Brilliant for a few weeks now. In the last few years, reading the works of Nassim Taleb on probability, randomness and complex systems rekindled my desire to learn probability and statistics. Instead of brushing off some rather dreary-looking textbooks in order to refresh my foundations, I decided to turn to Brilliant instead after stumbling upon its wonderful culture page.
The emphasis on learning by doing has been refreshing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reaction to Emily Wilson’s The Odyssey, Wonder and Education</title>
      <link>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/reaction-to-emily-wilsons-the-odyssey-wonder-and-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 21:38:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sunilvrao.com/posts/reaction-to-emily-wilsons-the-odyssey-wonder-and-education/</guid>
      <description>How I picked it up: Tyler Cowen named it his best book of 2018. Tyler called this a “joy to read” and praised Wilson’s introductory essay. I agree with this assessment, and I’ll add to this by singling out Wilson’ Translator’s Note, which I think is the book’s hidden gem:
“When I was eight years old, my primary school put on a production of a (much-shortened) Odyssey, complete with costumes, song, and dance…It was a turning point in my life.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
